<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Army's declaration: being a true alarum in ansvver to a false and fiery one made lately by a member of that destable [sic] Rump and printed for Livewell Chapman. By a member of the Army now in London.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3712A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1019_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867286</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867286</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119591</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119591)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 151:E1019[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Army's declaration: being a true alarum in ansvver to a false and fiery one made lately by a member of that destable [sic] Rump and printed for Livewell Chapman. By a member of the Army now in London.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for prevention of sedition and mutiny,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to an untraced work.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119591:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Army's Declaration: Being a True ALARUM IN ANSVVER TO A Falſe and fiery one made lately by
a Member of that deſtable RUMP And printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a member of the Army now in</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>Printed for prevention of Sedition and Mutiny, in the Year 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119591:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119591:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Armies Declaration,</hi> Being a true Alarum in anſwer to a falſe and fiery one,
made lately by that deteſtable <hi>Rump,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren and Fellow-Souldiers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen I conſider thoſe unparallel'd acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both of ſcandal and ſedition, thoſe many
changes and overthrows in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, thoſe ſtrange and horrid Oaths and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which
by the ſubtilty of a few turbulent and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious ſpirits, we have been ſeduced to make our
ſelves guilty of, how that by the knacks and pretences of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Uſurpers, we have almoſt
been the ruine of our native Countrey: and under pretence of liberty both of State and
Conſcience, have almoſt overwhelmed the Nation with Anarchy in State, and the ſtrangeſt
confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Church; whereby not only the glory of the Nation is decayed, but our ſelves
made infamous to all poſterity, if by our ſpeedy repentance, we do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from our
backſlidings, and with heart and hand joyne together, for the reſtitution of it to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
happineſs. When (I ſay) I conſider theſe things, I cannot but with the greateſt grief and
regret deteſt and abhor thoſe enormous crimes, which by the inſtigation and deluſion of our
Superiors we have day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119591:3"/>been guilty of, and are (it ſeems) again courted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by thoſe grand
contrivers of the Nations ruine, which as they have formerly, ſo (conceive) once more they
ſhall by their ſpurious mask of a Good old Cauſe, and defence of the good people of the Land,
the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretences of Freedom and Liberty, both as men and Chriſtians, and ſuch like
hypocritical cantings, ſeduce and draw us from the obedience of our General, and the real
authority; to the Egyptian bondage of an Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical tyranny, and to the inevitable ruine both of
our ſelves, and the Nation.</p>
            <p>Being truly ſenſible of theſe their machinations, which are not onely ſecretly carried
amongſt us, and the ſeeds of Sedition privately ſowed, but they are bold to give us loud
Alarums, and to our no ſmall ignominy proclaim to the world, that they conceive us fit perſons
for any villany, which can but cunningly be ſuggeſted to us, in defence therefore not onely of
my ſelf as a Member of the Army, but alſo of you my fellow-ſouldiers (whom I am confident
will unaimouſly ſubſcribe to what <hi>I</hi> have here written) I here preſent both you and
the world with a true Alarum, in oppoſition to that falſe fire which was lately ſhot in by
the Rump amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman (or as ſome ſay the Villain, <hi>T. Scot</hi>) begins his Libel with
ſomething to our purpoſe: ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by do often ſee more then the Gameſter, He little
conſiders how ample teſtimony we can give to the truth of this; not knowing I ſuppoſe, that
whilſt we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſo have been remote from their actions and
undertakings we have had leiſure and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to ſearch them to the depth, and find them to
be a crew of Atheiſtical, perfidious, and traiterous Raſcals,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119591:3"/>who whilſt they have by a cloſe and well-carried hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie made the glory
of God, and liberty of the people their outward pretences, have onely bent themſelves to
encreaſe their own eſtates, and perpetuate their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to the utter inſlaving of all
Engliſh men. He need not tell us he hath diſcovered more then many of us, when either he hath
not yet known, or elſe pretends him. ſelf ignorant, that we ſo far deteſt ſuch villanons
uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that we almoſt hate and loath our ſelves, for our ever being ſeduced and drawn
aſide by ſuch impudent and juggling Mountebanks</p>
            <p>I beſeech you Brethren, pardon my tranſportation, which I confeſs to be a little beyond
the bounds of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Reply; but what can a perſon deſerve at our hands, who hath
ſcandalized, and traitorouſly indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the ruine and deſtruction of our renowned
Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, who notwithſtanding the black-mouth'd envie of ſuch helliſh firebrands, will
ſtill be found to terminate all his actions in the peace and ſettlement of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and
Nation. But leaſt my Gentleman ſhould think he had too hard meaſure, and call this onely
railing at random, I ſhall take notice of ſuch particular heads of his papers, as may beſt
require an anſwer, or deſerve ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of.</p>
            <p>The Baſis on which he builds all the reſt of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is the old cheat and
juggle, wherewith we and the Nation were Gulled in 1648. Wherein, ſaith he, you ingaged and
promiſed, <hi>That you would ſee the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe Nations eſtabliſhed upon the
juſt and ſecure fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals and conſtitutions of Freedom: and Safety to the people, in
relation as they were men and Chriſtians, and that in the waies of a Common-wealth, and
Free-State-Government,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119591:4"/>without King, ſingle Perſon, or Houſe of Lords.</hi> This is that (which
the Gentleman endeavours to perſwade us throughout his whole Pamphlet) we are obliged to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſt in to our lives end; and in this cauſe undertaking ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we muſt (according to
his Opinion) onely expect the bleſſing and aſſiſtance of Almighty God; and to recede a
jot from this, is to turn Apoſtates from the cauſe of God, and to encur the danger of our own
ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not perplex the man with multiplicity of words, onely deſire him to ponder theſe
two particulars. Firſt, Whether his Maſters and fellow partners in iniquity, who were the
cauſe and promoters of this Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did not long before (not onely at their entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Parliament-houſe, but alſo ſolemnly in the ſolemn League and Covenant) ſware and
proteſt in the preſence of God, and the face of the world, that they would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the King
in his juſt Rights and Privileges, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his poſterity; and whether this was not the
onely ground and reaſon that we, and ſo many honeſt men in the Nation were induced to take,
up arms and aſſert their intereſt. Secondly, Whether it can be made out by the Laws of God or
man, that an Oath utterly unlawful in it ſelf, and wholly deſtructive to the good of a Nation,
ought rather to be kept, then repented of.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe neither he nor his Companions can be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent as to deny (though they have
been ſo impious as to forſwear themſelves) the firſt particular; but methinks I hear them
preſently ready to reply, that they intended no more by the taking that Oath, then the
maintenance and preſervation of themſelves and the people; and that they found it abſolutely
neceſſary for the good of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119591:4"/>to infringe and forget this their ſolemn Covenant: That they alwayes reſerved
to themſelves that mental reſervation, provided the ſafety of the King, might be for their
own, and the ſecurity of the good people of the Land: That where the Liberties of the Nation were
ſo highly concerned, there <hi>Salus Populi, ſuprema Lex esto;</hi> The ſafety of the people
muſt be the onely interpreter of all their reiterated Oaths and proteſtations; and upon theſe
ſpecious and guilded pretences they proceeded to the cutting off their lawful Soveraigne, and
craftily draw us in to be Bauds to their actions, whileſt we ſuffer our ſelves to be cheated
with thoſe Golden baits of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberties; and ſo whileſt we mean nothing but good,
cauſe us to perpetrate the height of' miſchiefs: Having broken the firſt Article of their
Oath, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Kings Majeſty, they preſently conclude there can be no way to
maintain their wicked actions, but by committing a ſecond as horrid and villanous, and ſo
proceed to the utter excluſion and baniſhment of his Poſterity; a crime which even the Turks
themſelves would be aſhamed to perpetrate.</p>
            <p>And now muſt we be drawn in to be compartners of their Villanies? they by all the canting
terms and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual expreſſions, the quainteſt of their Independent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents can invent,
repreſent the Kingly Government as arbitrary and tyrannical, and that England could never enjoy a
firm peace and ſecurity, but by the utter aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Monarchical Government; and we who
were only led by the blind faith we had in our (as we thought) Religious Commanders, are eaſily
drawn into the net, and ſuffer our ſelves to be caught in that ſnare, which have ſince
found, did intangle the Nation in ſuch fetters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119591:5"/>as have not been by any Power to be knocked off.</p>
            <p>But now ſince it hath pleaſed God of his mercy to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our eyes, and make us (by his
bleſſing upon our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral's indefatigable endeavours) in ſome ſort inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the
reſtoring of our Countrey from that bondage which ſhe hath by our deluſions long groaned
under; let not theſe impious and unparalel'd Traytors think us ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo ſottiſh as to
return with the Dog to his vomit, or ſo ſeired in our conſciences, as not ſeriouſly to
repent of our former miſcarriages. We confeſs we tooke an Oath to ſet up a Common-wealth; but
we never ſwore to deſtroy the Nation, we engag'd to defend the People of God, but never to
maintain a crew of Atheiſtical hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites: Nay further, We confeſs we engaged againſt a King
or Houſe of Lords, but did not by that intend the ruine of our Native Countrey; and when theſe
two come in competition, that either we muſt relinquiſh and recede from this our Engagement, or
elſe ſtill be made uſe of to enſlave our Countreymen, and utterly deſtroy our already
dying Stare: We cannot be ſo ſtupid and ſenceleſſy bewitched, not to think it better
ſeriouſly to crave pardon of God for this our Engagement, and the Nation for the wrong we have
hitherto done them, then by our obſtinate perſiſting in ſuch wicked Engagements, ſell our
ſelves to the Devil, and the Kingdom to ruine.</p>
            <p>The next point of this pious Gentleman's deſign, is no leſs, to make us turn abſolute
Rebels to our General, and upon this his grand endeavours are, under the notion of
Cavalier-Reports, to make him a deſigner of bringing and reſtoring the late King's Son. We will
not diſpute whether this be his insentions, onely we ſhall take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to tel the
Gentleman in a word, That we are no ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119591:5"/>Enomies to the Nation as he takes us to be, but do ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly reſolve, That if
it ſhall ſeem good to the Nation and our General to reſtore the baniſhed Prince to his
rightful Inheritance, we ſhall with one heart and hand readily ſubmit to, and concur with them
in it; and as we have been ſo ſignal for our diſobedience, ſo for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture endeavour to
teſtifie our ſelves true and loyal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to our Prince, and faithful and loving defenders
of our Countrey.</p>
            <p>In the next place our Libeller craftily endeavours to render our General odious to the
Presbyterian party, and like a wiſe man indeed, hath no other way to bring it about, but by
telling them he will and doth intend to bring in King <hi>Charles,</hi> as if that were ſuch a
Bug-bear to a ſober Presbyterian: but (ſaith he) <hi>if he be reſtored, there must
neceſſarily likewiſe throng in with him Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, and the reſt of that
Hierarchy, and they ſhall then be accounted no other by them, but Sectarians and Phanaticks,
&amp;c.</hi> Alas my friend! you are too well known for a lying impoſter, to be able to impoſe
any of theſe forgeries up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any ſober or godly <hi>Presbyterian</hi> whatſoever; nor is
there ſo great difference between a moderate <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> man, and a ſober
<hi>Presbyterian,</hi> but that both will jointly meet and kiſs each other, for the ſettlement
of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in peace and unity. But the man hath yet a fetch far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>The Queens Mother
will come, and then Moncks, Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its and Prieſts of all ſorts will ſhe bring with her, and
ſo Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will (cum Privilegio) be again readmitted into the Nation.</hi> I perceive that a
ſmall ſuppoſition is ſufficient for this Libeller to build a concluſion on; it is ten to
one whether ever the Queen return again, though the King be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Right, and ſhould
ſhe, yet cannot thoſe hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119591:6"/>ſervants ſhe brings with her, though they ſhould all be Jeſuits,
Prieſts, &amp;c. be ſo dangerous and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Religion as thoſe innumerable
multitudes of thoſe people who at preſent lurk in our Phanatick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles.</p>
            <p>His next particular conſiſts in advice and dehortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from thoſe perſons whom he
calls our beſts friends, and the good people of the Nations, thoſe whom he ſaith bled with
us, prayed for us, and been conſtant aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertors of the Intereſt of the Nation, againſt
King-ſhip, ſingle perſon, or Houſe of Lords; and what think my Brethren, are theſe our
ſo good friends, but thoſe who having made a gainfull bargain by embarking themſelves in a
quarrel againſt their Prince, do ſhiver at all thoughts of a reconciliation, leſt a
reſtitution of their ill gotten goods ſhould follow; and would now make us believe it is the
Intereſt of the Nation, though with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much expence of blood and treaſure; never ſo
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perjuries and acts of Rebellion, to maintaine theſe men in their wrongfully gotten, and we
might juſtly ſay as wrongfully detained Poſſeſſions and Acquiſts.</p>
            <p>But to proceed; they tell us, <hi>We are the onely Bulwark they must relye upon, and if we fail,
the Cauſe of God muſt ſinck with us; and that to bring our deſtruction about (and for no
other ends) the Militia throughout England is ſetled in ſuch hands as are perfect haters and
oppoſers of our Intereſt; and that above all others the Militia of London do threaten (as the
Danes were formerly ſerved) to make a black and bloody Night in cutting our throats, and offering
whole Hecatombs of our Carkaſſes to the reſtitution of</hi> Charles, <hi>whom they call their
King.</hi> Surely the Gentleman thinks we have as bad conſciences as themſelves, and that
becauſe we cannot
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119591:6"/>pardon our ſelves, the Nation can never be induced to pardon us; but let him
and his fellow Phanaticks know, That the Army hath no reaſon to feare the People of
<hi>England,</hi> when they ſeperate themſelves from their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted intereſt, and the Army
can expect no truer friend, or ſurer pay-maſter then the City or <hi>London,</hi> as long as
the army ſhall truly prove friends to the cauſe of the Nation; and that this Cauſe and the
Gentlemans are quite diſtinct things, the Voice of the people, and our own experience, wil
teſtifie.</p>
            <p>In the next place he indeavours to fright us to his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by telling us, that on whatſoever
terms the King may be brought in, and whatſoever fair pretences hee may make, yet at laſt all
muſt terminate in the loſs of our friends, wives, and children, and the for ever miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loving
of our poſterity. Alas, Sir, the cheat is now ſtale, and we underſtand our ſelves better
then ſo, as to think any man, much leſs the King, ſo ſtrange a maſter, that he muſt
ſacrifice us all to his luſt and revenge. Now we find where the ſhoo wrings; 'tis not the
ſouldiery are like to ſuffer by his reſtitution; no, 'tis a <hi>Scot,</hi> a
<hi>Haſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigge, a Walton,</hi> and ſuch, who having been already drunk with the blood of the
ſlain, and gorged themſelves with the plentiful diſhes of other mens eſtates, do now begin
to be terrified in conſcience, and to fear the diſgorging of their ſo ſweet morſels.</p>
            <p>But to track him a little further, he ſeems already ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like mad <hi>Tom,</hi> but now
turns right <hi>Tom Fool,</hi> and tells us that his Majeſties re-admiſſion muſt be
neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily deſtructive to the welfare of the Nation; and to prove this, he aſſerts the
vaſte charge the Nation muſt groan under, by the debts of his father, and himſelf,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119591:7"/>which remain unſatisfied. But ſee what a ridiculous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he makes. As
firſt, the Arrears of the King in his warr againſt the Parlament: but I beſeech the
Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to inform us where thoſe Armies are which ſhould receive thoſe Arrears, or thoſe
ſouldiers which ſhould demand their pay, or who ever knew that routed forces had ever any right
to demand their ſalaries.</p>
            <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> next is the young Kings charges in
<hi>Scotland,</hi> and at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> to which what I have already ſaid is
ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwer: ſo that the Gentleman muſt already be fain to ſubſtract above half
of his twenty years doubled impoſitions. The reſt, as the debts the King hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
beyond ſeas, the dowry of the Queen Mother, and the debts of his Brothers and Siſter, are
ſuch imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary trifles, that it is more then probable that leſs then the ſumme of a ſix
months Aſſeſſments, will defray the charges with an <hi>over-plus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the next particular, furniſhing and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Court and Train, I would
deſire the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to conſider what was ſaid in the Parlament Houſe, by a perſon, who
demanded of one of theſe pretended Common-wealths men, what he thought the charge of maintaining
themſelves, and keeping out the family of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> would yearly amount to; his
anſwer was, To twenty hundred thouſand pounds; Very good, repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the other, and I dare
undertake, that half that ſumme would bring him in, maintain him in a juſt ſplendor and
dignity, and defray the charges of the Nation beſides. And yet theſe impudent Cozeners would
make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that it were far better to keep him out with the intollerable oppreſſion and
taxation of the people; then by bringing him in to releaſe them from the greateſt part of their
burdens and miſery.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119591:7"/>
            <p>But to make up his bill of fare, he adds in the next place, That thoſe Dukes, Earls, Lords,
&amp;c. whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates have been ſold and diſpoſed by Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, muſt
either be reſtored, or ſatisfaction given for the ſame: Yes, here is that which bites to the
quick, and this is the real definitiod of their <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> But I deſire Mr.
<hi>Scot</hi> and his friends to conſider, whether, if they ſhould loſe all their ill-gotten
purchaſes, they can any way repine againſt God's juſt judgment, who ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never
continues ſuch unjuſt poſſeſſions to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third generation. But yet if
theſe men can pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently be quiet, and not by their new acts of treaſon againſt the quiet of
the Kingdome, irritate and incenſe the people againſt them, there will doubtleſs be found out
ſuch a medium as may make them no looſers, and yet the Eſtates return to the right owners;
for I would fain know, if that money which they purchaſed theſe Lands with, be returned to the
purchaſers, whether they will not be ſufficient gainers by having them ſo long in their
hands; or if this be too much, as indeed it is to be reaſon granted, I would fain know whether
the time they have already poſſeſſed thoſe Lands, hath not already paid them both
principal and intereſt; but there is another thing which theſe men fear, that is, divers of
them have purchaſed Crown, Church, and Delinquents Lands, and have agreed to pay at ſeveral
payments, &amp; ſome of them have never ſatisfied above the firſt portion; and theſe are
the men which fear (if account ſhould come to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) they might juſtly be adjudged to part
with theſe Lands at as trifling a price as they bought them; but I ſhall ſay no more as to
this particular, having (I doubt) too far intruded into matters of State, for a man of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119591:8"/>profeſſion of a private Souldier, but ſhall with the reſt of my
fellow-brethren acquieſce, as to this and all other points, in the determination of the joint
body of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not proceed much further, or meddle any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with the reſt of his rabblement,
which contains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but motions to Seditition, and the ready way to make us deſerve a halter;
but for his comfort do tel him, that we really proteſt againſt all ſuch mutinous thoughts and
are reſolved to live and dye with our worthy Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
            <p>But before I conclude, ſeeing the Gentleman hath been pleaſed to ſay ſo much to us, let
me be ſo bold as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a queſtion of him; Whether one grand reaſon of their being
Enemies to the King and a free Parliament, do not proceed from the conſciouſneſs of their
notorious cheating of the State, and privately pocketing up the Wealth of the Nation which was
raiſed and paid for diſcharging the arrears of the Souldiery, who in the mean time have
undergone all hardſhips and penury; and yet theſe Gentlemen can have the impudence to think
that we ſhould leave the aſſured hope of our pay, and be contented once more with their
imaginary promiſes, and that we ſhould forſake the ſervice of the nation in general, to
make our ſelves ſlaves and Janizaries to the arbitrary wills of ſuch blood-ſucking tyrants.
I have done with him; and if he conceive I have handled him too ſharply, let him know I have
diſcharged but the part of a Gentleman and a Souldier, to vindicate my ſelf and my
fellow-ſouldiers from thoſe deteſtable Titles of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains</hi> and
<hi>Mutiniers.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119591:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
